Fernando Romulo da Silva

Address: Rua do Monte Alegre nº 98 left, Zip Code: 4250-269, Cedo Feita, Porto - Portugal / Rua Paula Rodrigues,

 $\ensuremath{\text{n}^{\text{o}}}$ 250, Piratininga, Zip Code: 06233-030 bloco 16 apto 43 Osasco - SP - Brazil

Personal Page: https://fernando-romulo-silva.github.io/personal-page/

Cell Phone: +351 914-090-874 / +55 (11) 97046-6053

E-mail: fernando.romulo.silva@gmail.com

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I am a senior full-stack certified software engineer, highly motivated by new Java platform technologies. Although my primary qualifications are Java back-end and SQL databases, I have also worked with JavaScript front-end and NoSQL databases. I have experience in analysis, design, coding, testing (automated and manual), and delivering applications like REST and SOAP web services, web applications, batch jobs, web crawlers, and desktop applications. During my more than 15 years of experience, I have worked in a few business sectors like ERP, content management systems, employee benefits solutions, insurance provider solutions, credit reporting agencies (credit bureau), and financial solutions.

SKILLS

- Languages: I am a native Portuguese speaker and an upper intermediate English speaker.
- Java:
 - Versions: JDK5 until JDK17, GraalVm, DCEVM and HotSwapAgent.
 - Libraries: JUnit, TestNG, AssertJ, Mockito, HtmlUnit, JSoup, ApacheUtils, OpenAPI, OpenFeign, QueryDSL, Guava, etc.
 - ◆ **Tools:** Ant, Maven, Spotbugs, PMD, Checkstyle and Gradle.
 - Frameworks:
 - Spring: Spring Framework, Spring Boot, Spring Security, Spring Data, Spring Batch and Spring MVC.
 - JEE: JSF, EJB, JTA, JPA, CDI, JAX-WS, JAX-RS, JMS, batch Processing, etc.
 - Others: Swing, Quarkus and Hibernate.
- Version Control: Git, Github, Bitbucket and Gitlab.
- Java Script:
 - Version: JavaScript ES6.
 - Libraries: React, Lodash, Axios, Jest and JQuery.
 - ◆ Tools: JSLint, Npm, Yearn, Webpack.
- IDES: Eclipse, Dbeaver and Visual Studio Code.
- Data Bases:
 - **SQL:** Oracle, PostgreSQL, SQL Server and MySql.
 - ◆ NoSQL: MongoDB and Redis.
- **Servers:** Wildfly, Glassfish, Tomcat, and Jetty.
- Project Management:
 - Frameworks: Scrum (daily meeting, task breakdown, grooming, planning)
 - **Software:** Jira, Kanbanize, Microsoft Team Foundation and Redmine.
- Infrastructure: Virtual Box, Docker, Docker Compose, and Kubernetes.
- Messaging: JMS (ActiveMQ Artemis), Google Pub/Sub and Rabbit MQ.
- Cloud: Google Cloud Platform (GCP).
- Operation Systems: Windows desktop (all flavors) and Ubuntu Linux.
- Others: SOLID, Object Oriented Design, Domain Driven Design, UML, TDD and Design Patterns.

EDUCATION

• Postgraduate Degree - Software Engineering Specialization, 03/2018 - 12/2020

Pontifica Universidade Católica de São Paulo

Coursework with emphasis in software development and engineering using new technologies.

• Technical Course - W1 Desenvolvimento Avançado de Interfaces Web, 02/2014 to 03/2014

Global Code Treinamentos - São Paulo, SP - Brazil

Coursework to learn web technologies like Html5, XPath, JPath, Javascript, and JQuery.

• Technical Course - Curso Java para Desenvolvimento Web, 06/2009 to 09/2009

Caelum Ensino e Inovação - São Paulo, SP - Brazil

Coursework for learning Java Web technologies, JSP, Servlet, Struts, and JSF.

• Bachelor of Science - Computer Science, 03/2004 to 12/2006

UNOESTE - Universidade do Oeste Paulista - Presidente Prudente - SP Brazil

Coursework with emphasis on programming, develop computer tools, and software design.

CERTIFICATIONS

- Oracle Java EE 7 Application Developer
- Oracle Java SE 8 Programmer
- Oracle Certified Master, Java SE 6 Developer
- Sun Certified Java Programmer 5

WORK HISTORY

• Java Software Engineer, 04/2022

Dalenys - Porto - Portugal

I develop and fix cloud-native marketplace applications using Spring Boot, RabbitMQ, GCP, MongoDB, and MySQL Database Server.

• Java Software Engineer, 12/2019 to 03/2022

Boa Vista SCPC - Barueri, SP - Brazil

I developed cloud-native credit bureau applications using Spring Boot, Docker, Kubernetes, GCP, Google Pub/Sub, Redis, PostgreSQL, and MySQL Database Server. I improved Java applications using advanced docker and Spring resources.

• Java Software Engineer, 04/2015 to 12/2019

Fleetcor VB Serviços - São Paulo, SP - Brazil

I developed browser automation projects and employee benefits solutions using Java, JSoup, HtmlUnit, Spring, JAX-WS, JAX-RS, JBoss, Wildfly, Jetty, Tomcat, and Oracle Database Server. I used multi-thread processing (Java Executor Framework) to gain performance on web navigation.

• Java Developer, 06/2014 to 04/2015

BNP Paribas Cardif - São Paulo, SP - Brazil

I developed and maintained Java projects for insurance providers using Java, Spring, Web Services SOAP, Tomcat, Jetty, and SQL Server. I revamp various applications developed on Java core using Spring framework.

• Java Developer, 09/2009 to 12/2013

VB Serviços – São Paulo, SP – Brazil

I worked with employee benefits software solutions in JEE (JSF, EJB, CDI, JSP, Servlet, JMS, JAX-WS, and JAX-RS), Oracle Database Server, and Wildfly servers. I developed back-end software, batch applications, and sometimes, front-end pages server-side for most of my time.

• Java Developer, 04/2008 to 08/2009

Vetor Web - Negócios na Internet - São Paulo, SP - Brazil

I worked with content management systems done in JavaScript, JQuery, Java, JSP, JSF, Spring, Tomcat, and MySQL. I developed, for its time, advanced interfaces features using JavaScript and Java.

• **Delphi and SQL Developer,** 04/2007 to 04/2008

DB1 Informática Software e Consultoria – Maringá, Paraná – Brazil

I was a Delphi and Oracle SQL developer in ERP projects. I develop and fixing applications mainly for medium/large wholesale companies.

RECENT PROJECTS

Company: Dalenys

Project: Frontend Data Lake (New features)

Stack: JavaScript ES6, TypeScript, React 18, Axios, Jest, Yearn, EsLint

Role: Senior Software Engineer

Description: This a front-end application for the next project described. On this application, I fixed and

updated pages.

Steps: • Updated functions and layouts

• Update/create configs files

• Update the readme.md file

Company: Dalenys

Project: API for Data Lake (New features)

Stack: Java 17, Spring Boot 3.0, JUnit, AssertJ, MongoDB, RabbitMQ, Docker, Kubernetes and GCP

Role: Senior Software Engineer

Description: This API create scheduled reports that read data from a big data structure expose its

results on line. I intensively used automated tests to guarantee the quality of its

development.

Steps: • Create domains classes and tests

• Update/create services classes and tests

• Update/create endpoint classes and tests

• Update/create OpenAPI (Swagger) documentation

· Update the readme.md file

Company: Boa Vista SCPC

Project: API for Layouts (New Project)

Stack: Java 11, Spring Boot 2.5, Spring Security, JUnit, AssertJ, MySQL, Docker, Kubernetes and

GCP

Role: Senior Software Engineer

Description: This API provides file layouts on JSON and XML formats. These file layouts are used on

batch processing on GCP. Due to layouts having to follow strict rules, the application has to

validate a lot of situations; I used automated tests like unit (TDD), integration, and

acceptance tests (Spring Mock MVC) to solve this problem.

Steps: • Create domains classes and tests

• Create services classes and tests

Create endpoint classes and tests

· Create OpenAPI (Swagger) documentation

· Create the readme.md file

· Create Dockerfile with security and perfomance

• Create Kubernets yml files (service, deployement, kustomization)

Company: Boa Vista SCPC

Project: Batch Processing For Debts (New Project)

Stack: Java 11, Spring Boot 2.5, Spring Batch, JUnit, AssertJ, PostgreSQL, Redis, Docker,

Kubernetes and GCP

Role: Senior Software Engineer

Description: This is a batch application that reads some specific files, usually 10GB, treats and stores

the data (credit score) on a Redis Hashes. The business rules were simple, but some

analysis had to be done.

Steps: • Create domains classes and tests

· Create services classes and tests

· Create batch classes and tests

· Create the readme.md file

• Create Dockerfile with security and perfomance

• Create Kubernets yml files (service, cron job, kustomization)

Company: Fleetcor VB Serviços

Project: Benefits buyer (Maintenance)

Stack: Java 11, Wildfly, JEE, Spring Boot, OracleSQL, Docker

Role: Senior Software Engineer

Description: An upgrade for a web application, a web crawler. This project was a transforming

monolithic architecture towards micro service architecture. Only modules that made sense.

Steps: • Update domains classes

Update services classes

Create documetation

Create automated tests

Company: Fleetcor VB Serviços

Project: Communication Service (New Project)

Stack: Java 11, JMS, Spring Boot, MongoDB, Docker

Role: Senior Software Engineer

Description: This application is a communication broker for other applications. Its responsibility is to

send emails, SMS, etc, and manage the messages. It works as messaging consumer and

API.

Steps: • Create domains classes and tests

· Create services classes and tests

Create endpoint classes and tests

• Create OpenAPI (Swagger) documentation

• Create the readme.md file

Create Dockerfile with security and performance

• Create Kubernets yml files (service, deployement, kustomization)